（ユウ）目が覚めましたか。
Are you awake, our new king chosen by Eve?
イヴの選びし
われわれの新たな王　恙神　涯。
Gai Tsutsugami...
（涯）王？
"King"?
Mana will be reborn in Cocytus shortly.
間もなく　真名も
コキュートスに再生します。
This is the law of nature.
（ユウ）これは　自然の摂理。
The will of the very human race itself to evolve.
進化しようとする人類の
種　そのものとしての意思。→
あなたは　これから王になる。→
You are about to become king.
Neither you nor we can stop it.
あなたも　われわれも
それを止めることはできない。→
And, of course, neither can Mana.
むろん　真名も。
In other words, I'm not allowed to end?
終わることは
許されないというわけか…。
[無線]（ダアト将校）涯さま。　国連軍が
２４区に向けて移動を開始しました。
Master Gai, United Nations forces
have begun advancing on Ward 24.
- All right. Stand by until I get there.
- Yes, Sir.
分かった。
俺が行くまで待機だ。
[無線]はい。
Are you sad, Gai?
（いのり）悲しいの？　涯。
なぜ　そう思う？
What makes you think that?
（いのり）触った気がしたの。
Just now... it felt like your heart touched me...
今　涯の心が　私に。
俺は　悲しんでなどいない。
I'm not in the least sad.
My wish is going to come true at last.
ようやく　俺の願いが
かなうのだからな。
♪♪～
A symphony of disintegration resounds
The falling rain has the exact timbre of tears
Realize
Those eyes are for recognizing each other with
Those voices are for
conveying our feelings with
Those hands are for joining
hands with our loved ones
All you living beings who can hear this song
The truth lies within your heart
And even when you're traveling a stormy sea
It will give you a strength
That will never flinch
Eclosion
（倉知）ここまで接近して→
If we've come in this close
and they're not shooting, then...
撃ってこないということは
やはり…。
The 256 Leukocytes are a bluff.
（四分儀）２５６基のルーカサイト
というのは　はったりですよ。
われわれが　かつて
破壊し損なった１基と→
They have the one we failed to destroy before,
対光学観測のデコイやハッキングでつくり出した　まやかしです。
plus anti-optical-tracker decoys
and fakes put up by hackers.
（倉知）時間稼ぎか…。
So they were buying time.
まんまと乗せられて
われわれも　国連軍も→
And to think we and the U.N.
troops fell for it like fools
and sat on our hands
until the very last moment...
この　ぎりぎりのタイミングまで
手を　こまねいてしまうとは…。
But we made it in time.
（集）でも　間に合いました。
（集）それが　わずかな時間でも
僕らには　チャンスがあります。
Even if we haven't got long, we do have a chance.
いのりを助け出し
涯を止めるチャンスが。
A chance to save Inori and stop Gai.
That's right. If we secure her,
Gai's objective goes up in smoke...
（春夏）そうよ。　彼女を確保すれば
涯の目的は　ついえ→
日本人のみならず　世界中から→
And we might even be able to
eradicate the Apocalypse Virus...
アポカリプスウイルスを
駆逐する可能性も見える。
not just in Japan, but all over the world.
私たちには　悲観すべき未来しか
残されていないわけではないのよ。
We aren't stuck with a bleak future yet.
そうですね。
「世界の運命が」なんて→
Yes... I never thought I'd
find myself unironically saying
"the fate of the world lies in our hands,"
真面目に言うことがあるとは
思ってませんでしたが→
but it seems this is that sort of battle.
これは　そういう戦いのようです。
Let's win it. No matter what.
勝ちましょう　必ず。
I'm borrowin' this, Ogumo.
（アルゴ）借りてくぜ　大雲。
Can we make this protocol work, Mama Haruka?
（鶫）このプロトコルで　いけます？春夏ママ。
We should be able to,
if they haven't discovered us yet.
そのはずよ。
まだ発見されてなければ。
（綾瀬）手伝ってもらってもいい？
Could you give me a hand?
うん。
Yeah.
（綾瀬）ねえ　集。
うん？
Hey, Shu.
（綾瀬）撃てる？→
Could you shoot?
If Gai were right in front of you,
could you pull the trigger?
もし　涯が　目の前に現れたら
撃てる？
Yeah, I could.
撃てるよ。
綾瀬は奇麗だよね。
You're so radiant, you know?
な…！
いきなり　何　言ってんのよ！
Where did that come from?!
汚れるのは　僕の役目なんだ。
It's my job to get dirty.
So you stay pure and radiant, Ayase.
だから　綾瀬は
奇麗なままでいてよ。
Shu...
集…。
But I know if it's time to fight, I'll use your Void.
とはいっても　戦いになったら
僕は　きっと　君のヴォイドを使う。
So maybe I'm still making
you an accomplice, but...
結局は　同罪に
しちゃうのかもしれないけど…。
構わないわ。
That's fine.
I knew what I was getting into
when I left my heart in your hands.
そのつもりで
私の心を預けたんだもの。→
ただし！
あげたわけじゃないんだからね。
But I didn't give it to you, got it?
借りっ放しで
絶対　勝手に死なないでよ！
So don't you dare go
and die without returning it!
ありがと　綾瀬。
Thanks, Ayase.
[無線]（国連兵士）攻撃隊　全機
間もなく　ポイントデルタに到達します。
All attack units will arrive
at Point Delta momentarily.
（艦隊司令）全エンドレイヴ
降下を開始せよ。
All Endlaves begin your descent!
All units begin descent!
[無線]（国連兵士）全機　降下開始！
全機　降下開始！　ゴーゴーゴー！
All units begin descent! Go, go, go!
（城戸の口笛）
（城戸）すっごい数だなぁ。
There's sure a lot of them.
They seriously hate you, huh Gai?
本気で憎まれてるね　涯。
やるぞ。
- I'm doing it.
- Be my guest.
（城戸）好きにしなよ。
フッ！
♪♪～
あっ…。
（ダアト兵士）目標の８７％を撃破！
Target 87% destroyed!
Not a peep from the enemy!
（ダアト兵士）敵は　完全に沈黙！
（茎道）大勢は決した。　残りを
片付けるのは　われらの仕事だ。
The overall outcome has been determined.
It's our job to mop up the rest.
（茎道）「全エンドレイヴを起動。
ゴースト部隊を出撃させろ」
Start up all the Endlaves. Mobilize the Ghost unit.
（ローワン）頼むよ　ダリル少尉。
I'm counting on you, Lieutenant.
Hey, what are you even doing here, anyway?
（ダリル）ねえ　あなたさ
何で　ここにいんの？
あいつらのお仲間ってわけでも
なさそうだけど。
It doesn't exactly sound like you're on their side.
And you? Why volunteer to be a guinea pig
after fighting the idea so hard?
君こそ
あんなに抵抗していたのに→
どうして　自分から　モルモットに
志願するようなことを？
Wouldn't anybody be pissed off
if their Void kept beating them?
だって　悔しいじゃん？
ヴォイドに　やられっ放しっての。
それに　死に方くらい
自分で選びたいしね。→
Plus, I want to at least
choose how I die for myself.
行こうか
ゲシュペンスト。
Shall we go, Gespenst?
国連軍には　もう少し
頑張ってもらいたかったのですが。
I wish the U.N. Forces
had held out a little longer...
急ぎましょう。
Let's hurry.
♪♪～
Here we go!
行きます！
（ダアト兵士）第７区画に
新たな敵が上陸！→
New enemy landing in Block 7!
It's not the U. N!
国連軍ではありません！
葬儀社か！？
Funeral Parlor?!
ゴーストを回せ！
Send in the Ghosts!
やったか？
Did we get them?
フン。　違うね。
あれはヴォイドだ。
Nope. That's a Void.
コピーが　やられた！
They took out the copies!
I'd anticipated that.
（四分儀）想定済みです。
Tsugumi, that should have been enough
for you to analyze their security setup with.
鶫。　今ので　セキュリティーの
構造解析には十分だったはずです。
やれますか？
Can you do it?
Who do you think you're talking to?
I blow some minds when I get serious!
（鶫）誰に言ってんの？
私の本気は　ちょっと　すごいよ。
あっ！　あった！
春夏ママのバックドア。
There it is! Mama Haruka's back door.
≪（アラーム音）
（ローワン）何が起こった！？
What just happened?!
Our system's been infiltrated!
（ダアト兵士）
システムに侵入されました。
They've...
動きが…。
...stopped moving?
止まった？
Don't waste this chance! Get our boots
on the ground and suppress them!
この好機を逃すな！
制圧用の歩兵部隊を上陸させろ！！
Souta!
颯太！
≪（シャッター音）
Ａ４エリアに上陸されました！
Teams have landed in Area A4!
≪（ダアト兵士）連合艦隊
さらに接近中！
The combined fleet is moving in closer!
くっ！　復旧を急げ！
Hurry up with those repairs!
（鶫）それじゃ　みんな
ここで　お別れね。→
Okay, guys, this is where we part.
Don't worry, I'll screw them up
royally and guide you all to safety.
いっぱい　連中の邪魔して
みんなを安全に誘導するからね。
Right.
ああ！
頼むよ　鶫。
We'll count on you, Tsugumi.
ちゃんと　いのりん助けなよ。
You just better save Inoreen.
Then we'll all have a happy end, you hear?
そんで　みんなで
ハッピーエンドだかんね！
これから　お前という人間を
構成していた→
I'm about to erase all the memories and emotions
that constituted you as a person.
記憶と感情は　全て消失する。
あ…！
You're going to be reborn as Mana.
お前は　真名として生まれ変わる。
Resent me, Inori.
俺を恨め　いのり。
俺が　あのとき
お前を目覚めさせなければ→
If I hadn't awakened you then,
nothing would have begun...
何も始まらず→
...and nothing would have ended, either.
そして　終わることもなかった。
ううん。
No... I'm grateful to you, Gai.
涯には　感謝してるの…。
だって　あなたは
私に　人生をくれた。
Because... you gave me a life.
You let me meet Shu.
集と出会わせてくれたんだもの…。
あっ。
うっ…！　うわぁぁ！→
あぁぁ…！
綾瀬！
（綾瀬）「任せて！」
Ayase!
Leave it to me!
What did Shu give you?
集は　お前に　何をくれた？
お前に
どんな世界を見せてくれた？
What sort of world did he show you?
この世界の悲しさ…。
This world's sadness... and... its beauty.
それと　美しさ…。
Shu suffered, and doubted, and made mistakes,
集は　苦しんで　迷って　間違って→
自分の醜さを恥じて…。
and he was ashamed of his ugliness...
でも　私が好きなのは…。
But the reason I love him is...
あっ…。
Shu's human. He's heartbreakingly human.
集が　人だから…。
悲しいくらい　人だから…。
（綾瀬）「集！　もう　やめて！」
いいんだ　綾瀬。
Shu, that's enough!
It's okay, Ayase.
バカ！
You idiot!
だから　私→
That's why... even though I'm only a vessel...
入れ物でしかないのに…。
なのに→
I still got to... fall in love...
普通の人…　みたいに→
like a normal... person...
恋…　できたの…。
≪（銃撃音）
（アルゴ）鶫！
チェックポイント到着。　次は？
Tsugumi, we're at the checkpoint! What's next?
Tsugumi, where are you?!
鶫！　どうした！？
The security's back up again?!
セキュリティーが復活してる！
（倉知）システムを奪還されましたね。
They've recovered control of the system from us.
チッ！　どこだ？　いのり！
Where are you, Inori?
≪（銃撃音）
それが　お前の集への思いか。
So those are your feelings for Shu?
集…？　誰？
Who's... Shu?
お前が愛した男の名だ。
That's the name of the man you loved.
♪♪「咲いた　野の花よ」
♪ Blooming wildflower ♪
♪♪「ああ　どうか　おしえておくれ」
聞こえる…。
♪ I beg you, please tell me ♪
I can hear it.
あぁ？
いのりの歌だ！
That's Inori's song!
♪ Why do people fight and hurt each other? ♪
どうしたんです？　彼は。
歌なんか　何も…。
What's happened to him? I don't hear any song...
こっちだ！　ついてきて！
This way! Follow me!
集にだけ…。
そうね。　可能性はあるわ。
Only Shu hears... Yes, it's possible.
行きましょう。
どのみち　他に指針はないんです。
Let's go! We don't have anything
else to navigate by anyway!
（颯太）慌てないで！
ゆっくり移動してください！
Stay calm! Walk, do not run!
♪ Valiantly blooming flower ♪
♪♪～
♪ What can you see from your field? ♪
♪ Why can't people forgive each other? ♪
ここは…！？
Where are we?
中央作戦司令室よ！
ここからなら　最上階にも直接…。
This is Central Command! We can
get straight up to the top floor from...
あっ。
≪（物音）
Welcome, Shu Ouma.
（ユウ）ようこそ　桜満　集君。
ならびに　その従者の皆さん。
And all your followers, as well.
従者じゃねえ！　仲間だ！！
We ain't "followers"! We're comrades!
ここ千年　そういう概念が
はやっていることは知っています。
Yes, I'm aware that such concepts have
been in vogue over the past thousand years.
（ユウ）僕たちは→
There's something the two
of us need to talk about alone.
２人で話さなくては
いけないことがあります。→
従者の皆さんとは
残念ながら　ここでお別れです。
I'm afraid it's time to part with your followers.
（綾瀬）「集！」
僕は大丈夫。
Shu!
I'll be fine! You protect everyone else!
それより　みんなを守って！
Well, aren't you looking fine now?
（ユウ）ずいぶん立派な姿に
なりましたねぇ。→
救世主というやつですか。
You're supposed to be a "savior," I take it?
君は…　いったい　何なの？
Who are you, exactly?
僕は　人類の意思を決定する機関
ダアト。→
I am a symbol of the unity of Daath,
その総意を象徴するものです。
the organization which derives
the will of the human race.
いわば　僕こそがダアト。
You could say that I myself am Daath.
When you brilliantly recovered all by
yourself the kingly power stolen from you,
（ユウ）あなたは　奪われた王の力を見事　自ら回復してみせ→
われわれは
再度　検討することになった。
we were forced to reexamine the question
あなたと涯　どちらが→
of whether you or Gai would be
the best Adam, the next king.
アダム　次なる王に
ふさわしいかを。→
よって　桜満　集。　われわれは
これを君に問わなくてはならない。
Therefore, Shu Ouma, we must ask you this:
人類が　次のステージに進むために全ての人類を滅ぼし→
In order for mankind to
progress to the next stage,
you will vow to obliterate all mankind
未来永劫
真名と２人で生きることを→
and live with Mana for all eternity, won't you?
誓ってくださいますね？
What are you talking about?
何を言っているの？
Answer with "yes" or "no," please.
答えは　イエスかノーで。
No.
ノーです。
That's the normal answer.
それが普通です。
しかし　恙神　涯は→
However, Gai Tsutsugami answered
"yes" without even batting an eye.
眉一つ動かさず
イエスと言ってみせた。→
That's the difference between you and him.
そこが　彼と　あなたの差です。
Now then... In the name of Daath,
（ユウ）では→
ダアトの名の下に　君から
継承者の資格を剥奪します！
I hereby strip you of your right of succession.
うわぁ！
ああっ！
谷尋！
Yahiro!
♪♪～
うわー！
（アルゴ）あっ！　出口か？
An exit?
（ダリル）「そうだよ。　でも…」
Yep. But...
You won't ever reach it!
（ダリル）「君らは　永遠に
たどりつけないけどね！」
（綾瀬）「あっ！　まさか　あんた…」
（ダリル）その　まさかさ！
Don't tell me it's you?!
You'd better believe it.
（ダリル）
「決着つけようぜ　葬儀社！！」
Let's settle this, Funeral Parlor!
淘汰と進化は
この星の生命の避け得ぬ運命です。
Selection and evolution
are the inescapable fate of all life on this planet.
逆らっても無駄だというのに
君は！
To resist them is futile, and yet you...
うーっ！
うわぁ！
You refused Mana after she did
you the honor of choosing you.
せっかく　真名に選ばれながら
彼女を拒んで→
揚げ句　楪いのり…
あんな　まがい物に入れ揚げて！
And in the end, you squandered
everything on a fake like Inori Yuzuriha...
You're wrong!
違う！！
うあーっ！！
アルゴ！
Argo!
ぐうぅぅぅ！！
いのりのことを
みんな　知らないんだ。
None of you know Inori.
誰も　彼女のことを知らない。
Nobody knows her.
いのりは→
Inori fought the ugliness inside her,
自分の中の醜さと闘って
苦しんで…。
and she suffered...
（ダアト兵士の　うめき声）
同じように　間違えて傷ついている僕を　そっと支えてくれた。
And when I hurt from making
the same mistakes, she gently supported me.
フッ。
いのりだけが　ずっと　そばにいて
僕を信じてくれたんだ！
Inori's the one person who was by
my side the whole time, believing in me!
だから　今度は　僕が隣にいる。
今度こそ離さない！　いのりーっ！！
So this time, I'll be by your side.
And this time, I won't let you go...
...Inori!
ハッ！
（ユウ）ならば　やってみるがいい
桜満　集。　絶望への抵抗を。
Go ahead and give it a try, then,
Shu Ouma. Try resisting despair...
You just missed her.
一足　遅かったな。
あ…。
Mana will be reborn by devouring Inori.
いのりを糧に　真名が復活する。
Our lost Eve!
失われた　俺たちのイヴが！
The Apocalypse is upon us, then?
始まるのか…
黙示録のときが！
そんな…！
No...
♪♪～
What am I supposed to care about,
left behind alone in a world like that?
♪♪～
I spent so many days,
accumulated so many feelings
And you were by my side the whole time,
A fixture of my life, and when you left,
I discovered their weight for the first time
If I'd gripped your hand tight
that day and not let go...
In the end, I was only living
in my own self-satisfied world
"Now it's like I'm a liar
for saying I did it all for you"
Even those murmured words don't reach you
Run, run to you
Watch, I'll fall as often,
get lost as often as it takes
Wait for me, because I'm on my way
No matter what difficulties are waiting there